Imagine if you had three wishes, three hopes, three
dreams and they all could come true.
Aladdin is a animation, family, adventure film directed by John Musker.
In the boorish city of Agrabah, kind-hearted street urchin Aladdin and
Princess Jasmine fall in love, although she can only marry a prince.
He and power-hungry Grand Vizier Jafar vie for a magic
lamp that can fulfill their wishes.
Aladdin (voice), played by Scott Weinger.
Genie / Peddler (voice), played by Robin Williams.
Jasmine (voice), played by Linda Larkin.
Jafar (voice), played by Jonathan Freeman.
Iago (voice), played by Gilbert Gottfried.
Sultan (voice), played by Douglas Seale.
Aladdin is a 1992 American animated musical fantasy film based on the
Arabic folktale "Aladdin" from One Thousand and One Nights.
Produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation, it was directed by John Musker and Ron
Clements, both of whom co-wrote the screenplay with Ted Elliott and Terry Rossio.
The film features the voices of Scott Weinger, Robin Williams, Linda Larkin,
Jonathan Freeman, Frank Welker, Gilbert Gottfried, and Douglas Seale.
The story follows an Arabian street urchin named Aladdin, who discovers a magic lamp containing a genie, with whose help he disguises himself as a wealthy prince and tries to
impress the Sultan of Agrabah to win the heart of his free-spirited daughter, Princess Jasmine, as the Sultan's evil vizier, Jafar, plots to steal the magic lamp.
Lyricist Howard Ashman pitched the idea to Disney Studios president, Jeffrey Katzenberg, and the
screenplay went through three drafts before Katzenberg would agree to its production.
The animators based their designs on the work of caricaturist Al Hirschfeld, and computers
were used for both finishing the artwork and creating some animated elements.
Composed by Alan Menken, the musical score features six songs with lyrics written by
both Ashman and Tim Rice (who took over following Ashman's death).
Aladdin was released on November 11, 1992, to critical and commercial success: critics praised the animation and Williams's performance as the
Genie, and it became the highest-grossing film of the year, with an earning of over $504 million in worldwide box-office revenue.
On release, it became the first animated feature to reach the half-billion-dollar mark, and was the fifth highest-grossing film at the
time of its release and the highest-grossing animated film of all time until it was surpassed by The Lion King (1994).
Aladdin garnered two Academy Awards, as well as other accolades for its soundtrack, which had the first number from a Disney feature to
earn a Grammy Award for Song of the Year, for the film's "A Whole New World", sung by Peabo Bryson and Regina Belle.
The film's home VHS release set a sales record, grossing
approximately $500 million in the United States.
Aladdin's success led to various derived works and other material inspired by the film, including two direct-to-video sequels,
The Return of Jafar and Aladdin and the King of Thieves, an animated television series, and a Broadway adaptation.
A live-action film adaptation directed by Guy
Ritchie was released on May 24, 2019.
The film explores themes of princess, magic, tiger, cartoon, villain.
The tone is emotional.